# Yuanyue Li, Ph.D.

West Coast Metabolomics Center University of California, Davis 451 Health Sci Drive Davis, CA 95616, US

E-mail: gccli@ucdavis.edu

Website: <a href="https://yuanyue.li">https://yuanyue.li</a>

GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/yuanyueli">https://github.com/yuanyueli</a>

## PERSONAL STATEMENT

Metabolites are fundamental components in biological processes, yet their large-scale detection remains a big challenge, limiting our understanding of metabolomics. My research aims to bridge this gap by integrating mass spectrometry with computational strategies to enhance metabolite identification techniques. I am interested in the development of innovative computational tools and the integration of machine learning strategies for large-scale metabolite structure identification. In tandem with this, I am interested in integrating metabolomics with other 'omics' like proteomics and genomics to better understand the function of metabolomics, thereby enhancing our knowledge of life science and human health.

## **EDUCATION EXPERIENCE**

# Ph.D. in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology

2008.9-2014.6

Xiamen University, Xiamen, China

Thesis title: A novel analysis method for data-independent acquisition MS data

**B.Sc. in Life Science** 2004.9-2008.7

Xiamen University, Xiamen, China

# **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

#### University of California, Davis

Davis, United States

Postdoctoral Fellow / Assistant Project Scientist, advisor: Dr. Oliver Fiehn

2020.1-now

Focus: Mass Spectrometry-based Metabolomics

- Designed and implemented Flash entropy search algorithm, magnifying the speed of library searching by five orders of magnitude.
- Introduced the concept of spectral entropy and entropy similarity to the mass spectrometry field, reducing the false positive rate in metabolite identification by up to 40%.

# **European Molecular Biology Laboratory**

Heidelberg, Germany

Postdoctoral Fellow, advisor: Dr. Peer Bork

2015.12-2019.3

Focus: Proteomics and Metabolomics

- Invented SF-Matching, a machine learning-driven approach to improve metabolite identification.

- Established a strategy coupling proteomics and metabolomics techniques to unsupervised identify protein-metabolite interactions.

Xiamen University Xiamen, China

Graduate Student, advisor: Dr. Jiahuai Han

2008.9-2015.6

Focus: Mass Spectrometry-based Proteomics

- Developed Group-DIA, an approach that enhances protein identification notably by grouping multiple mass spectrometry datasets.

#### **PUBLICATIONS AND AWARDS**

## Main author publications:

- 6. **Yuanyue Li** & Oliver Fiehn. Flash entropy search to query all mass spectral libraries in real time. *Accepted by Nature Methods* (2023) doi:10.21203/rs.3.rs-2693233/v1.
- 5. **Yuanyue Li**, Tobias Kind, Jacob Folz, Arpana Vaniya, Sajjan Singh Mehta & Oliver Fiehn. Spectral entropy outperforms MS/MS dot product similarity for small-molecule compound identification. *Nature Methods* 18, 1524–1531 (2021).
- 4. **Yuanyue Li**, Michael Kuhn, Joanna Zukowska-Kasprzyk, Marco L. Hennrich, Panagiotis L. Kastritis, Francis J. O'Reilly, Prasad Phapale, Martin Beck, Anne-Claude Gavin & Peer Bork. Coupling proteomics and metabolomics for the unsupervised identification of protein–metabolite interactions in Chaetomium thermophilum. *PLOS ONE 16*, e0254429 (2021).
- 3. Yuanyue Li, Michael Kuhn, Anne-Claude Gavin & Peer Bork. Identification of metabolites from tandem mass spectra with a machine learning approach utilizing structural features. *Bioinformatics* 36, 1213–1218 (2020).
- 2. **Yuanyue Li**, Chuan-Qi Zhong, Xiaozheng Xu, Shaowei Cai, Xiurong Wu, Yingying Zhang, Jinan Chen, Jianghong Shi, Shengcai Lin & Jiahuai Han. Group-DIA: analyzing multiple data-independent acquisition mass spectrometry data files. *Nature Methods* 12, 1105–1106 (2015).
- 1. Chuan-Qi Zhong\*, **Yuanyue Li**\*, Daowei Yang, Na Zhang, Xiaozheng Xu, Yaying Wu, Jinan Chen & Jiahuai Han. Quantitative phosphoproteomic analysis of RIP3-dependent protein phosphorylation in the course of TNF-induced necroptosis. *Proteomics 14*, 713–724 (2014). (\* equal contributions)

#### **Contributing author publications:**

- 7. Elys P. Rodríguez, **Yuanyue Li**, Arpana Vaniya, Patrick M. Shih & Oliver Fiehn. Alternative Identification of Glycosides Using MS/MS Matching with an In Silico-Modified Aglycone Mass Spectra Library. *Analytical Chemistry* (2023) doi:10.1021/acs.analchem.3c00957.
- 6. Panagiotis L. Kastritis, Francis J. O'Reilly, Thomas Bock, **Yuanyue Li**, Matt Z. Rogon, Katarzyna Buczak, Natalie Romanov, Matthew J. Betts, Khanh Huy Bui, Wim J. Hagen, Marco L. Hennrich, Marie-Therese Mackmull, Juri Rappsilber, Robert B. Russell, Peer Bork, Martin Beck & Anne-Claude Gavin. Capturing protein communities by structural proteomics in a thermophilic eukaryote. *Molecular Systems Biology* 13, 936 (2017).

- 5. Xiurong Wu, Wan-Ting He, Shuye Tian, Dan Meng, **Yuanyue Li**, Wanze Chen, Lisheng Li, Lili Tian, Chuan-Qi Zhong, Felicia Han, Jianming Chen & Jiahuai Han. pelo Is Required for High Efficiency Viral Replication. **PLOS Pathogens** 10, e1004034 (2014).
- 4. Ting Wu, **Yuanyue Li**, Deli Huang, Felicia Han, Ying-Ying Zhang, Duan-Wu Zhang & Jiahuai Han. Regulator of G-Protein Signaling 19 (RGS19) and Its Partner Gα-Inhibiting Activity Polypeptide 3 (GNAI3) Are Required for zVAD-Induced Autophagy and Cell Death in L929 Cells. **PLOS ONE** 9, e94634 (2014).
- 3. Xiurong Wu, Lili Tian, Jie Li, Yingying Zhang, Victor Han, **Yuanyue Li**, Xiaozheng Xu, Hanjie Li, Xi Chen, Jinan Chen, Wenhai Jin, Yongming Xie, Jiahuai Han & Chuan-Qi Zhong. Investigation of receptor interacting protein (RIP3)-dependent protein phosphorylation by quantitative phosphoproteomics. *Molecular & cellular proteomics* 11, 1640–1651 (2012).
- 2. Hanjie Li, Congting Ye, Guoli Ji, Xiaohui Wu, Zhe Xiang, **Yuanyue Li**, Yonghao Cao, Xiaolong Liu, Daniel C. Douek, David A. Price & Jiahuai Han. Recombinatorial Biases and Convergent Recombination Determine Interindividual TCRβ Sharing in Murine Thymocytes. *The Journal of Immunology* 189, 2404–2413 (2012).
- 1. Duan-Wu Zhang, Min Zheng, Jing Zhao, **Yuan-Yue Li**, Zhe Huang, Zhu Li & Jiahuai Han. Multiple death pathways in TNF-treated fibroblasts: RIP3- and RIP1-dependent and independent routes. *Cell Research* 21, 368–371 (2011).

## **PRESENTATIONS**

#### **Invited oral talk:**

2023.08	(Upcoming) Chinese American Society for Mass Spectrometry Conference
2023.02	University of Ottawa
2022.06	JRNLclub.org
2022.03	National Center of Protein Sciences, China
2022.02	Metabolomics Association of North America SODAMeets
Oral talk:	
2022.10	Chinese American Society for Mass Spectrometry Conference
2021.10	Metabolomics Association of North America Annual Conference
2020.09	NIH Common Fund Metabolomics Consortium Meeting
Poster:	
2022.06	American Society for Mass Spectrometry Annual Conference
2021.09	NIH Common Fund Metabolomics Consortium Meeting
2020.09	Metabolomics Association of North America Annual Conference
2020.05	American Society for Mass Spectrometry Annual Conference